So what we will start looking at today is
what.
.
Right so what we call immediate RL immediate
reinforcement having problems so if you remember
I said there are many, many characteristics
of a reinforcement learning problem and one
of those was that you get this evaluation
from the environment and could potentially
be delayed right so I said you might actually
lose a piece very important piece in the middle
of a chess game but you get a reward only
at the end it is not like the final move you
made it someone that causes you to lose it
could be somewhere along the way right.
So what we are going to do now is to actually
consider a much simpler version of the problem
where we do not have this the temporal nature
to it right, so we are not we are not going
to assume that the rewards are the scalar
evaluation that comes from the environment
is going to come at a further time than when
the action is actually performed right so
I am going to assume that as soon as you perform
an action like you are going to get a evaluation
right and that is it basically right.
So we are going to consider a much more simplified
version of the problem that is at every time
instance I am required to pick an action right,
so every time instant T right I pick an action
at right, and then I receive a reward RT and
that is it my interaction is ended right.
So I can learn something from this interaction
and go back and pick a another action at time
t + 1 right so that is why we call this immediate
reinforcement learning problems because the
outcome is immediate so as soon as if take
an action I get a reward right.
So what else is missing in my description
here there is no real input to the system
right there is no state signal that the system
is seeing so all the input it is getting are
the rewards right there is no state input
to the system right, so it is like it's just
solving the same problem again and again right
so instead of thinking of it as not having
a state you could think of it as having like
every time I give it the same input and I
am asking you to give me a action in response
to that this is seem like a reasonable thing
to have you think of cases where this might
actually be an appropriate model.
So one example which people give us in drug
testing right so I have I have a certain symptom
that is presented to me right and I can choose
on one of four different drugs to treat that
symptom right so I first I give Doug one it
may or may not cure the person if it cures
the person then I get a reward if it does
not cure a person I do not get a reward right
but it could very well be that for a variety
of reasons the person did not get cured it
is not because that the drug one was not the
right give for this person right.
For this symptoms but for a variety of other
reasons the patient might not have been cured
so I cannot conclude by just administering
the drug once that the drug is ineffective
for a set of symptoms and I have to keep trying
the drug multiple times right before I can
come to a conclusion that the drug is ineffective
or a person okay alright so for a certain
set of symptoms so it is like saying that
okay there are multiple you know samples that
I have in a lab and each of them is exhibiting
the same disease.
Let us not talk about human beings administering
drugs and killing them or something can think
of what samples in the lab right I'm going
to add some drugs to that and see if that
particular organism dies right in that in
the when I add the drug and so far it is essentially
the same presentation as far as the drug testing
is goes right it is the same organism that
I am trying to kill say microorganism that
I am trying to kill across all of these different
instances it is like the same state that is
being presented to me over and over again
but then I have multiple choices that I could
make and as soon as I do the choice I get
a feedback saying okay.
Yeah the organism died or it did not die right,
so I have to keep trying this multiple before
I figure out which is the right drug to administer
okay good it clear so that gives you an example
right so there are a couple of things which
I kind of rolled into their example as well
so one of the is this that the outcome can
be stochastic right, so every time I take
an action right so I did not be given the
same evaluation back right so I take a tissue
sample added up to it right so i might not
succeed every time right so sometimes I will
succeed sometimes I might not succeed so that
is some kind of a stochastic nature to the
outcome right.
So as a consequence of the stochastic nature
what did you have to do I have to repeat things
multiple times right so this is these are
things which you have to keep in mind when
we are talking about this kind of immediate
reinforcement learning problems that we are
going to have a stick outcomes and then we
have to think about repeating choices multiple
times before we can be sure of the outcome
right is there anything else that was that
could have been critical to the successful
outcome of this let us say that I tried drug
one okay.
And the organism survived okay, so then I
just can I keep using drug one for all the
other organisms as well let us say let us
keep the problem simplified I just will say
heavily to drugs drug or drug too okay I take
the first organism give it drug one its advice
I take the second organism give it to does
not survive okay, now can I conclude that
which one is more effective during go in order
to win do not know me assuming is oneself
the survival what we are looking for not survey
well what we are looking for not survival
talking about microorganisms he is right I
actually flipped it around I do not know but
nobody actually noticed it.
So yeah so I am looking for non survival of
a microorganism right so in this case drug
to appear to be more effective than drug one
right so that does not mean I can keep giving
drug to all the other samples and I need to
actually go back and try drag one a few times
right so this is the exploration and I was
telling you about exploration in the previous
class size this is the exploration here that
I have to do exploration so the critical thing
here that even the simple case of this immediate
reinforcement learning introduces to is the
need for exploration right but can I just
keep exploring can I just keep giving random
drugs to each of the samples and at some point
I have to stop right.
I am interested actually in killing this microorganism
today at some point I have to stop and I said
okay here this is the actual drug that is
going to kill the microorganisms and I have
to start giving that drug right this did not
be an explicit point where I stopped we will
see as we go along but I am interested in
eventually exploiting the knowledge that I
am acquiring about this the whole system right,
so either I explore or I have to at some point
I have to stop and start exploiting so there
is his inherent tension between exploration
and exploitation okay.
They are in some sense at loggerheads with
each other right if I stop at some point and
say okay I have know enough about the system
and then I start exploiting then I necessarily
have to stop my exploration right but then
if I do not explore enough I will be exploiting
a poor solution right so this exploration
exploitation so sometimes people call it a
conflict sometimes it is called the called
the Explorer exploit dilemma right so too
should I explore Philly explain so that is
essentially what this immediate reinforce
will any problems captures for okay.
Since this is a very crucial question in reinforcement
learning so we will look at this immediate
reinforcement learning problems in a little
bit of detail so that it will motivate some
of the other things that we will do later
when we move to the full RL problem right
and so what I will do which is slightly different
from what is there in the textbook, so how
many of you have actually looked at the textbook
good see I did not ask how many of you have
read the book right.
So what I will do the slightly different from
the book and I am still not decided whether
it will be for both versions of the course
let us talk a little bit more about some of
the critical questions that people are interested
in addressing in the immediate RL setting
right.
It is a book just gives you a very algorithmic
very prescriptive viewpoint of this right
this is or here is how you solve the immediate
reinforcement learning problem right it does
not go beyond that it does not give you anything
about right so why do people solve it the
way they do it I will go a little bit beyond
that and try to give you some way intuition
in that mainly because that seems to be a
very active area of research nowadays in reinforcements
and many of the ideas that people are using
there are also being transferred to see the
full reinforcement learning setting.
The one with all the delayed rewards the states
and things like that right so lot of ideas
from the research in this immediate RL setting
is also being used to the full URL setting
so I want to introduce you to those topics
right, yeah so despite the makeup of the class
right just predominantly undergrad this is
a graduate level course rate so I want you
to want to introduce people to research questions
and other things Sarah mean demands for I
to actually teach an advanced trouble codes
at some point I know at least one person who'll
take it I am going to try this.
Now every class I am going to make people
turn and look at you at least once I manage
to do that last class anyway so go back so
we will look at a little bit of formalism
on this right so what I am going to assume
is that I have a set of actions A which will
index by 1to n so action one could be anything
right and this is just giving the arbitrary
numbers 1 to n it could be drug one drug to
drug three it or it could be add one add two
add three whatever it is just one point is
what we will denote it as right.
And each action when I pick that action it
gets a payoff it is an evaluation so I am
going to be using these terms interchangeably
right reward payoff evaluation cost so all
of this denote the same thing that dotted
line that came in my box diagram right so
depending on what literature you come from
you use different by different names for it
right so the reward typically comes from guess
psychology it cost comes from control theory
optimization yeah payoff comes from econ economics
and what is the last thing I say evaluation
comes from optimization okay fine.
So depending on which, which background you
come from you give it different names right
and so I will use them interchangeably for
example for most of this literature I will
be using payoffs because a lot of the work
has been done in the in the o, r and economics
community in when they are trying to analyze
these kinds of problems right so when you
pull each when I actually select an arm I
select an action right what's going to happen
is that I will get a reward or a payoff sample
from some unknown distribution so what do
I mean by that stochastic but what do I mean
more I mean it can right this is something
which I found people have difficulty so some
people at least have difficulty when I say
it is sample from a distribution so what I
mean by mean is the following.
Let us keep it simple so that people can conceptualize
it so associated with each action let us say
that I have a coil associated with each action
there is a coin okay that has some probability
of coming up heads and some probability of
coming up tails so let us some probability
P of coming up as they say pick action one
then there is a probability P one of coming
up heads when it toss the coin right and I
will say that if the coin comes up heads ok
I will give you a payoff of one if the coin
comes up tails I will give you a payoff of
0 right.
So every time I select an action I am going
to toss this coin so depending on whether
it comes up heads or tails I will give you
either a one or a zero right so the payoff
that I will get every time I select that action
is not the same right but what is same the
coin right if I select actual action one I
will always toss coin one if is elect action
5 and always toss coin five right I am not
changing these coins okay, is it clear does
it make sense to people and I will not change
the coins but the coins will be the same right.
But every time I pick action I will toss that
coin and I will give you the payoff or reward
corresponding to the outcome of the coin toss
so if I say that the probability of reward
for picking action 1 is 0.8 what does it mean
a probability of heads of the associated coin
is point eight right in this case I can go
further I can also say something else I can
say that the expected payoff of picking action
one is point eight as well right because the
probability pointed will get a reward of 1
with the probability point2 will get a reward
of 0 so if I take the expectation of this
it will get will be point eight right.
We will understand this now so when they say
select an arm select an action I will tell
you why I keep calling it off in a second
and then I will keep calling it up so when
I select an action right then I am going to
toss a coil right depending on the outcome
of the coin I am going to give you one this
is something which you should remember when
you are actually going and implementing these
things right so I had people do all kinds
of weird things right and make sure that you
remember what I mean when I say you sample
from a distribution okay great.
So now I gave you the simple example of tossing
a coin I could actually have any complex distribution
right so if a toss a coin what is the distribution
I am sampling from enrolling right I could
have other kinds of distributions I could
have a Gaussian distribution let us say so
now what does it mean for every action I choose
okay.
So for action when that is going to be a like
some kind of a Gaussian distribution right
and so what is the axis here x axis here the
payoff the payoff for the reward x axis the
payoff for the river and the y axis is the
probability that you will see such a payoff
right so that is the most probable pay off
as it also happens to be the forgotten this
also happens to be the expected payoff right
so how will I sample from a Gaussian they
can add a number and 0 and anyone else have
a sample from a Gaussian okay.
How do you do that people who are in my minor
I told you how to do this in the class okay
little bit more efficient we have to get yeah
and then what you do?
Do not tell me you smite lab no man it is
your role you know too many terminology just
keep throwing them around go to CMC stand
for in then there are two emcees then you
just told me a Monte Carlo I said give me
something more efficient and then he keeps
saying another Monte Carlo method what is
it no one oh come on, fine okay Paulo you
tell me, so the guys who were in the guys
were there in my minor rights I actually told
you how to sample me remember I said so I
did this with a discrete distribution and
then I told you how to do this with continuous
distributions as well can you give the me
write-up on model okay.
So basically the idea is you generate a random
number right between 0 and 1 generate a uniform
random number between 0 and 1 right and then
keep integrating the area under the curve
what is it called the CDF right and then when
the CDF reaches that random number you generate
so that is the number you sample does it make
sense, so this is a complete aside.
.
Let us say that I have four possible outcomes
right I want to generate one of those four
outcomes at random right so the probabilities
are p1 p2 p3 p4 how will I do that I generate
a uniform random number between 0 to 1 right,
no so I will see if the number is less than
P1 if the number is less than P1 I will generate
outcome 1 if the number is between p1 and
p2 and generate the outcome of two this number
is between p2 and p3 l generate the outcome
of three generate number is between p3 and
p4 is it correct or not, it should be between
p1 and p1 + p2 okay it should be between p1
plus p2and p1 plus p2 plus p3 so it should
be the cumulative sum right it should be the
cumulative some previous cumulative sum and
the next cumulative sum.
So if it lies between that then that is the
outcome I will tend right so is less than
P1 I will generate one if it is between p1
and p1 plus p2 I will generate two if it is
between p1 plus p2and p1 + p2 plus p3 I will
generate three if it is between p1 + p2 +
p3 and one I will generate four right do not
tell me if p1 + p2 +p 3 + p4, so you can simulate
the CDF for the question right yeah so there
are ways of doing it right so there we have
doing this so you can do this for any probability
distribution for which you can define the
CDF.
Not just Gaussian it's not just discreet so
the discrete case it is very clear right so
what you are doing is essentially cumulate
adding up the probability so whenever you
hit that number you say that is the Nazi sample
that you have drawn right in this case you
just do this oh my gosh she is okay so this
is what I mean when I say sample from a probability
distribution again it is not the most probable
outcome like a nice a sample from this Gaussian
I have actually seen people implement okay
the reason I keep reiterating this people
actually form the Gaussian and then keep returning
the value that has the highest probability
right.
So please do not do that of course if you
are using MATLAB or something like that you
don't even have to think about it we can just
say Rand N and then it will give you a sample
from a normal distribution which is what she
was going to tell you what is the way to sample
from a Gaussian but this is what it does internally
wait and to give you the sample having said
this now you can go back to using random yeah
we had a question okay fine so going back
associated with each of these actions right
I am going to have some distribution from
which the payoff Is being sampled okay is
it clear.
And these distributions I am going to assume
at least initially will be fixed for the duration
of the experiment for duration of the learning
this distributions will be fixed like I said
you do not change the coin you don't change
the Gaussian also okay now if I knew the Gaussian
then or if I knew the coin send you the probability
with which the coin will turn up tails heads
right so how will I solve the problem there
is no problem right I just picked the action
that has the highest mean right highest mean
and for the Gaussian or the highest p 1 for
the coins right whatever it is the highest
expected payoff I just picked a topic that
action right.
So the challenge comes when I do not know
the distributions all I know is that is some
distribution which I am assuming is fixed
according to misty payoffs are generated I
do not know the distribution so I basically
have to figure out the distribution and then
pick the pick the action I picked action corresponding
to that right so is it clear so for each of
these actions right for each of these actions
I am going to assume that that is a true expected
payoff which will denoted by Q* of A.
Let us say it's action so Q* is a function
that will give me the true expected payoff
of action a right so in the case of the coins
Q star of one will give me p 1 this is a probability
of heads that Q star of 2 will give me p2and
so on so forth in the case of Gaussians Q*
of one will give me µ1 let you star of 2
will give me Bo 2and so on so forth and see
what the Q* function is this is again unknown
to me and if I know Q*I am done right I am
a problem is solved right but this the assumption
we are going to make so we have a set of actions
A and we have a set when corresponding Q*
that we do not know about right.